Preliminary Guide to the James R. Hawkins Papers, ca. 1961-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James R. Hawkins papers ca. 1961-1980
Hawkins, James R.
15 linear feet Extent: 7800 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00520
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection has recieved minimal processing and is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Gift of James R. Hawkins, 1983.
Biographical Note
1925 Mebane North Carolina
1943-1946 Served in the U.S. Marine Corps
1951 Graduated from Duke University
1956 President, Durham Junior Chamber of Commerce
1959-1967 Durham City Council Member
1969-1970 Chairman, Research Triangle Planning Commission
1970 Vice President, North Carolina Association of Realtors President, Durham Chamber of Commerce
1971 Mayor of Durham, North Carolina
James R. Hawkins worked as a realtor in addition to being involved in municipal politics and service organizations in Durham, North Carolina. He served as a City Council Member in Durham from 1959-1967 and was Mayor of Durham in the 1970s.
Collection Overview
The subject files, correspondence, and published materials in the James R. Hawkins Papers span from ca.1961-1980, chiefly 1971-1975, and document Hawkins' role in civic life in Durham, North Carolina and provide evidence of the issues and concerns facing the citizens of Durham in the 1970s. The subject files retain Hawkins' original folder titles and alphabetical organization and provide an overview of the programs Hawkins was involved with as mayor as well as a view of the general issues Hawkins encountered while mayor of Durham. The correspondence series is arranged alphabetically and chiefly consists of letters to Hawkins from the citizens of Durham voicing their concerns over such civic issues as development, traffic safety, taxes, and various political issues. The correspondence also contains copies of Hawkins' responses to the letters he received from the citizens of Durham. This collection would be of value for scholars studying the recent history of the south or for those wishing to gain a clearer picture of the functioning of city government in the recent past. This collection is open to researchers and has received a minimal level of processing.
Subject Headings
Hawkins, James R., 1925; Municipal Government -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Mayors -- North Carolina -- Durham
Contents of Collection
- Accession 1986-0001
  The subject files, correspondence, published materials, and other miscellaneous items in this collection generally relate to city government and the history of Durham, North Carolina. The wide variety of subjects addressed by the files held by James R. Hawkins reflect the various issues that concerned the citizens of Durham, and Hawkins as its mayor, during the early1970s.
  - Subject Files (Box 1)
    The material held in the Subject Files Series serves to document the issues facing James R. Hawkins while he was mayor of Durham form 1971-1975.These files hold a variety of material formats including correspondence, clippings, reports, studies, and proposals relating to city programs and issues that Hawkins dealt with as mayor. The Subject files are in alphabetical order.
    - Alcoholic Rehabilitation (Box 1)
    - Allied Arts (Box 1)
    - Annexation (Box 1)
    - Annexation Program, 1965, Jan.-June (Box 1)
    - Ernie Barnes (Box 1)
    - Bicentennial (Box 1)
    - Bicentennial News (Box 1)
    - Bikeways (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information (Box 1)
    - Budget (Box 1)
    - Business Development Company of Durham, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Cable Television - Analysis of Bids (Box 1)
    - CAC - Citizens Advisory Committee (Box 1)
    - Cane Creek - Chapel Hill (Box 1)
    - CATV - Cable Television (Box 1)
    - Wade Cavin (Box 1)
    - Central Business District Redevelopment (Box 1)
    - CETA - Comprehensive Employment Training Act, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - Chamber of Commerce, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Charter of the City of Durham (Box 1)
    - Child Advocacy Commission of Durham, Inc. (Box 1)
    - City Clerk (Box 1)
    - City Council (Box 1)
    - City-County Charter Commission (Box 1)
    - City-County Comm. File [Utilities] (Box 2)
    - City Hall [Building Plans], (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - City Magazine (Box 2)
    - City of Durham - Compensation Plan (Box 2)
    - City of Durham - Miscellaneous 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - City of Durham - Miscellaneous1973, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - City of Durham - Miscellaneous1974, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Civil Preparedness (Box 2)
    - Code Enforcement Project [Building Codes] (Box 2)
    - Code of Ethics (Box 2)
    - Committees - Council and Citizen (Box 2)
    - Community Development Program, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Community Planning services of Durham (Box 2)
    - Consolidation Program, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Courthouse Feasibility Study Committee (Box 2)
    - Convention Center Site (Box 2)
    - Creek Hazard Study (Box 2)
    - Cultural Center - County Courthouse (Box 2)
    - Dog Ordnance (Box 3)
    - Downtown Durham, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Drug Abuse (Box 3)
    - Duke Power (Box 3)
    - Duke University Hospital - Board of Advisors, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Durham City Council - Economic Development Report (Box 3)
    - Durham Community Cannery (Box 3)
    - Durham, England (Box 3)
    - Durham Hotel (Box 3)
    - Durham Housing Authority (Box 3)
    - East End Neighborhood Housing Committee (Box 3)
    - Eastern Airlines (Box 3)
    - East-West Expressway (Box 3)
    - EPA Grant Application (Box 3)
    - Educational Information Corp. (Box 3)
    - Election Requirements (Box 3)
    - Energy Committee (Box 3)
    - Energy Crisis (Box 3)
    - Eno River, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - EPA - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 3)
    - Equal Opportunity Employment (Box 4)
    - Finance Department, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Fire Department (Box 4)
    - Flat River Reservoir, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Flood Plan Information (Box 4)
    - Gas Crisis, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Glenn Road Landfill (Box 4)
    - Growth Options (Box 4)
    - Growth Policies (Box 4)
    - Handicapped, Mayor's Committee for the (Box 4)
    - Health Department (Box 4)
    - Highway Commission, State, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Holhauser, James E., Jr. (Box 4)
    - House Bill 75 (Box 4)
    - HUD - Department of Housing and Urban Development (Box 4)
    - Human Relations Commission (Box 4)
    - I-40 [Interstate 40], (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Industrial Development and Per Capita Income in NC (Box 4)
    - Junked Car Ordinance (Box 4)
    - Legal Opinions - City Attorney, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Legislative Commission - NC League of Municipalities, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Legislative Commission - NC League of Municipalities (Box 5)
    - Library (Box 5)
    - Local Government Commission (Box 5)
    - Low-Income Housing (Box 5)
    - Manpower Advisory Committee (Box 5)
    - Manpower Project, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Manpower Project - Region J MAPC Committee (Box 5)
    - Mass Transit (Box 5)
    - Massage Business Ordinance (Box 5)
    - McManis Report (Box 5)
    - Mobile Homes (Box 5)
    - Martin Luther King Freedom Games (Box 5)
    - Mayor's Manpower Assistant (Box 5)
    - National League of Cities (Box 5)
    - National League of Cities - Affective Government Committee (Box 5)
    - Natural Gas (Box 5)
    - New Hope Basin - Wastewater Collection and Treatment (Box 5)
    - Nixon, President Richard (Box 5)
    - North Carolina Department of Revenue (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Department of Water and Air Resources (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Drug Authority, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - North Carolina League of Municipalities (Box 6)
    - North Carolina League of Municipalities - Board of Directors (Box 6)
    - North Carolina League of Municipalities - Open Meetings Law (Box 6)
    - North Carolina League of Municipalities - Regional Affairs Comm. (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Legislature (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Manpower Council, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Museum of Life and Science (Box 6)
    - North Carolina Symphony Orchestra (Box 6)
    - Off-Street Parking Committee (Box 6)
    - Operation Breakthrough, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - Pan-Africa-USA International Track Meet (Box 6)
    - Personnel (Box 6)
    - Police Department (Box 7)
    - Proclamations1973 (Box 7)
    - Proclamations1974 (Box 7)
    - Proclamations1975 (Box 7)
    - Program for Progress (Box 7)
    - Project for Redevelopment (Box 7)
    - Property File, Durham City-County (Box 7)
    - Public Safety Program (Box 7)
    - Public Works (Box 7)
    - Raleigh-Durham Airport Authority, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Rape Crisis Center (Box 7)
    - Recreation Department (Box 7)
    - Region J - Triangle J Council of Governments, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Region J - Triangle J Council of Governments (Box 8)
    - Region J - 208 Study (Box 8)
    - Regional Health Plan, 1974-1975Edition (Box 8)
    - Report on Water and Sewer Rates, February1961 (Box 8)
    - Research Triangle Water Line (Box 8)
    - Residential Choice Task Force (Box 8)
    - Revenue Sharing, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Revenue Sharing, Hearings, October 8,1975 (Box 8)
    - Revenue Sharing - NLC Revenue Sharing Evaluation Subcom., (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Revenue Sharing - NLC Task Force, Jan. 29,1975 (Box 8)
    - Revenue Sharing - NLC Task Force, May 8,1975 (Box 8)
    - School Board (Box 8)
    - School Merger (Box 8)
    - Senate and House (Box 8)
    - Snow Removal (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste Study (Box 8)
    - Southern Newspapers Publishers Association (Box 8)
    - Subdivision Review Board (Box 8)
    - Traffic Department (Box 8)
    - Transportation and Utilities (Box 8)
    - Travel Expenses, James R. Hawkins, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Triangle Center for Voluntary Action (Box 8)
    - Triangle Housing Development Association (Box 8)
    - Triangle J Council of Governments - Annual Work Program Summary (Box 8)
    - Triangle J Council of Governments - Steering Committee (Box 8)
    - Triangle J Council of Governments - Transportation Committee (Box 8)
    - Triangle J - 208 Study, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - United States Conference of Mayors (Box 9)
    - Urban Reinvestment Program (Box 9)
    - Urban Study (Box 9)
    - USAF - United States Air Force (Box 9)
    - USA - Pan-Africa - West Germany International Track and Field Meet (Box 9)
    - USGA - Junior Tournament (Box 9)
    - USSR-USA Track Meet (Box 9)
    - Water Resources (Box 9)
    - Water Resources - City of Raleigh (Box 9)
    - Wellons Water System (Box 9)
    - Workable Program (Box 9)
    - Youth Opportunity, Mayor's Council on (Box 9)
    - Youth Meeting (Box 9)
  - Publications
    The Publications Series includes reference works, general works of non-fiction, and governmental reports whose subject matter addresses the sorts of issues that Hawkins faced in the early1970s.
    - Administrative and Financial Laws for Local Government in NC, 1973 (Box 9)
    - City Centers in Transition, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Costs of Sprawl (Box 9)
    - Federal Budget and The Cities, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Future of the South (Box 9)
    - Housing and Community Development, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Popular Government, 1975 (Box 9)
    - National Municipal Policy, 1975 (Box 9)
    - United States Budget in Brief - Fiscal Year 1976 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence Series contains letters from constituents expressing concerned opinions about community issues, such as redevelopment plans, road repair, and tax. In many cases this series also includes copies of Hawkin's responses to the letters. The letters are filed in loosely chronological order.
    - Miscellaneous1971, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous1972 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous1972, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous1974, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous1975, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Invitations Accepted/Declined 1971-1977, (12 folders) (Box 10)